so I thought we could continue with the
maim series but skipping ahead quite a bit
series but skipping ahead quite a bit
to um discourse number
131 and it's actually there's four
discourses that are the same 132 133 134
mhm and it's called one good
night so I'll read the verse that um is
found in each of those sutors
one should not dwell on the past nor
hope for the
future the past is over and the future
is yet to
arrive one who sees clearly presently
Arisen things should train their mind to
not be caught or moved
there that task should be done today for
tomorrow death may come there is no
negotiating with death's death's Mighty
Force by living day and night with such
uncompromising effort the peaceful sage
has declared one to have a good night
mhm and that verse is found in each of
those sutors repeated in just in
different contexts um and then the
contexts um and then the
questions that follow is how does one
you know chase after or the
past and it says one Delights in
thinking I had such a form I had such a
feeling I had such a perception I had
such Aggregates I had such experiences I
had such experiences oh it was like this
back in the day and was so that's
delighting in those that's how you yeah
but as is often heard
in spiritual circles is like don't think
about the past and it comes kind of this
kind of verse can make it sound like
don't sure forget about the past forget
about it but this is thinking in you know does
it but this is thinking in you know does
say thinking
delighting delighting in those past
things almost nostalgic
about to bit up than that it's not just
being nostalgic
um so can you stop thinking about the
past can you just not think memories
memories it's part of you exactly it's
impossible yeah impossible so see when
people try to people should stop um
dwelling through Delight on the
past people stop taking PATH for
granted but it doesn't mean you should
stop thinking about it as in like as if
as if that's an option that you could
just stop thinking about it and not
think about the past you could choose
not to dwell on it you could choose not
to Delight in it you could choose not to
welcome it MH but you can't choose not
think it because you are
it so when people say stop thinking
about the past they overshoot the mark
because they want to stop dwelling on it
but they can't see the middle ground
where dwelling stops without trying to
get rid of it and then they just go too
far and try to get rid of it
m how do you find the middle ground
where the past
is do you need to go back into the
past no because that's so say you're
thinking about the past you think about
a past event yeah that your mind wants
to Delight in it was so great and you
want to relive it again
where is that experience it's presently
isn't it's right now it's right here
that is its framework doesn't matter how
far in the past you go it is presently
like you're presently thinking it it
can't be any other way but see when you
overlook the fact that you're presently
thinking any past possible when you
overlook that fact you are in the
past like your thoughts imply this was
back then in that time in in that
place not here
anymore you don't see the heess so to
speak of it still here because here
you're thinking it now you're thinking
it and it always has been that way so if
you begin by not losing that
perspective on the presently that
whatever past you might be thinking it
can only be thought presently there is
no past
thinking then try the same in the future
and if future thought that you're
planning for tomorrow see if you
overlook the fact that that is present
here now while you're thinking it you
will imply that those thoughts are the
thoughts of tomorrow and for tomorrow
and they're over there and they're more
in the future than they're here and
that's why you start blaming the
thoughts oh stop thinking about the
future oh don't don't don't don't think
about the past it's like those are just
thoughts in the present why would there
be a
problem so once you see that whether
it's the past whe is the future whether
it's the present it can only be thought
presently you you are then completely um
aligned with what verses say you should
do because it's not like oh I should do
these things presently no you just need
to stop overlooking that they are
already present it can't be any other
way and that's another thing that people
that would be blaming the thoughts
blaming the past blaming the future just
stop thinking about it don't dwell on it
and so on just just just be in the
present moment that's another thing they
miss the fact that you can't be anywhere
else except in the present moment so it
it does not need to come from your
volitional effort of being
present if it actually comes from that
effort you are not present you're not
aware of that effort being the present
moment so you're doing the present
moment on your own terms through your
own craving through your own Notions no
you find the frame work of the present
moment which is already there and you a
put
second any notion of me I was I will be
it's second to it
m that's why the WD would always so
convey that by saying oh he does not DW
and think like oh I was in the past I
was such in the past I had such form I I
me me me but if you still think like
that even if you think the present
moment you're thinking it through me me
me me me which is not really the
framework of the present
moment say yeah so how does one
anticipate the future one Delights in
thinking may I have such a experience
such a form such a feeling such a
perception so and then how is one caught by
so and then how is one caught by
presently AIS States how is one caught
and moved he says here an ordinary person
moved he says here an ordinary person
who is unskilled in the noble Dum and
discipline views each of the Aggregates
or views experience as as self as as if
or as possessing that the self possesses
these things self is in those things
those things are in self either way his
sense of self his I am is the center
point is the reference for any
permutation the self has to be there one
way or the other yeah so even so
whatever you are experiencing you caught
there but you could you could the same
like when you think about
yourself whatever ambiguous thoughts you
might have or images or
Notions there it is what are those
thoughts other than thoughts yeah so
it's like oh so the self is not real no
the self is real as a thought as an
image that you've been misconceiving and
attributing far more than it actually
is but it yeah you have the genuine
notion of I am
it's a real thing but it's an image as
such it's a thought it's presently being
enduring there and you're thinking it
you're perceiving it as an image that is
its existence any other implication that
that image might have of me importance
my own I am all of that is now second to
the mere image of it
yeah and that's how you start correcting
that order and I say
and you won't be getting caught in
thoughts of the past yeah or thinking
about less and less you'll be caught
less and less because you're not caught
here and now exactly you don't have that
view that yourself is beyond or if you
are here not seeing yourself as an
Arisen thing that endures on its own as
an image as a
thought then you will be implying
yourself in the past and you will be
anticipating yourself in the future cuz
that is it Gateway that is what it comes
through and then and as
it's so what is the that task should be
done today well because when else can you do
today well because when else can you do
it
yeah for tomorrow death may come is
already there is it's still a cont you
know death is going it's going to happen
yeah and but the time ask one I think
well what is the what is the task
there there's no there's no instruction
here there's no but it's just one who
sees clearly presently aison things
should train their mind to not be caught
Yeah so basically the Su is instructed
for those who have the right view yeah
who see who sees correctly present and
things not somebody who's still stabbing
in the dark yeah who SE they who see
Damas as Damas who see things correctly
who have the right view should then make
the effort to not be
caught to not slip up to not lose the
context and and start carelessly
thinking about their form in the past
anticipating in the future dwelling on
it in the
present so then what is
uh seeing in
image how do you know you're seeing an
image seeing dumbers as dumbers how do
you know you're seeing it things as they
are or presently Arisen thing well are
you free from
suffering is there
no that sharp tip of pain they can get
you regardless of the pain regardless of
the circumstances regardless of the
thing that's regardless of the thing
that's risen yeah
yeah
so it's not a metaphysical or a
theoretical or abstract notion I mean
obviously it is for people but no seeing
Damas is Damas means basically being
able to see your mind as
mind and that's already a prerequisite
for S about and how do you see your mind
as mind well we covered that in many
other sutas you got to
first round it up fence it off tie it
down let it kick and scream urinate in
defecate in in in in anger and threats
because you're restraining it and then
when it comes down then basically you
you present it with things that
arise and start training it to get used
to
it get used to the context that you
don't want to think about get used to
the inevitabilities that you distract
yourself from But first you need to have
tamed it down through virtue and sense
restraint need to be able to Simply put
up with saying no to the desires no to
ill will no to the distraction
and once it's able to do that you bring
up the context of sickness death various
contemplations in the sutas not for some
great resolution expectation as I said
in the previous talk but simply bring it
up so the mind can look at it and then
see what the Mind does same you want to
train a dog or like the Su say you train
a battle elephant you don't immediately
throw it into the battle but you don't
like keep it sheltered from the spears
either so once it's there obeying you to an
so once it's there obeying you to an
extent then yes you put some weight on
it see what it does see whether then he
wants to run back to the Wilderness then
correct it when he gets used to it then
they start proing it with sticks then
with Spears then with all these little
things to train it to Simply remain
there composed and unperturbed basic
basically thoughts of deaths thoughts of
the inevitability thoughts of
inevitability sorts of things you don't
want to think about basically losing
your loved ones losing your wealth
losing your your your your health losing
your life just things you're generally
things people are generally intoxicated
with you could just start thinking about
them and probably would have some effect
but generally if your behavior is still
contradicting these very Notions of of
kind of dispassion and
impermanence uh you won't get very far
you might just wind yourself up and
become neurotic basically but if you do
start saying no to your
desires ill acting out of ill will
keeping the precept uh restraining
yourself then as I said the mind is
contained even if it doesn't feel
Pleasant it's contained and then when
these things come up these thoughts
these contexts you don't try to get rid
of them you don't distract yourself you
don't fall into views of psychologizing
them and explaining the reasons why
these thoughts came up you just leave
them there as a cloud hanging over a
village while everybody in the village
continues about the
day so you leave this context in front
of the animal and let it continue you
know now obviously it's a bit Freer
because it's sort of semi- tained you
let it move and you watch its reactions
until it gets used to it until it
doesn't care whether the cloud is there
or not then you bring a bigger
Cloud then you amplify the
cloud and the point will come when
nothing will move it
MH that's the training training the Mind
mov up with
and the more immovable the mind is the
clearer the images are the clearer the
thoughts are the clearer the nature of
the past is the clear the nature of
anticipation is all of that just starts
falling into
place it's not really like a a complex
logical secret that you need to decipher
in order to understand it the reason it
does not land where it should land is
because the mild is no mind is nowhere
near being
tamed so you can't bear those images let
alone see through them and and and their
implications and their
nature it's not used
to just bearing with little discomfort
sorry just it's not used to bearing just
even a little bit of well no it might be
used to bearing a lot of discomfort on
the physical level but bearing
discomfort is not the same as enduring
on the right level when I say I keep
saying that because keep people keep
confusing it um the point is enduring on the right
it um the point is enduring on the right
level means enduring that certain mental
ambiguity SL anxiety SL discomfort only
on that certain mental level that's why
the Buddha himself said no sometimes I
eat two bowls of food and sleep in
King's palaces so he endures no
discomfort yeah and he has disciples
that would be eating just a like a like
a grain of rice and sleep sleep under a
tree and wear rag Gres yet they still
respect him they still value his
teachings it's obviously not because of
bearing the elements on its own it's
because they understood what the right
level is according to his teaching and that is
is according to his teaching and that is
what's freeing them and that's why they
respect him and that right level is that
mental level and as I said many times
like people would rather be putting up
with far worse factually worse physical
pains torment enduring on that physical
level then to have just like a nagging
thought of Doubt or what do they think
of me like for example or was that what
you know what what do you mean when he
said that these little unresolved things
these little mental pressures that's
more unbearable that will make people go
crazy that usually those things come up
in solitude yeah does yeah so I would
rather just mindlessly you just beat me
and give me some some physical bearing
task sit immovable for 10 hours and and cry
sit immovable for 10 hours and and cry
through pain but mentally I can switch
off mentally I will switch off but
having an doubt or a worry or an anxiety
waking me up at
night 24/7 oh that's far worse well
that's the right level so if you're
practicing on that level building it up
through right taming as I said precepts
sense restraint watching your speech
avoiding entertainment moderation in
eating increasing Solitude you wouldn't
need to do any of the other stuff you
wouldn't even you probably occasionally
you might have to bear some elements
just to see if anything will come up but
it's going to be insignificant in Min
skill